NCAA Tournament Seed Prediction
Technical Design Video
Hi, I'm Om. In this video I'll walk you through
my NCAA Tournament Seed Prediction model.
How it works, why I made specific design choices,
and how it performs on real data.
The problem: given 68 teams in the NCAA tournament,
predict each team's overall seed from 1 to 68.
Seed 1 is the best team.
Seed 68 is the last team in the bracket.
This is harder than it sounds. We're not predicting
seed lines — we're predicting exact overall ordering.
There are four 1-seeds, four 2-seeds, and so on.
The ordering between them matters. That's 68 unique positions.
The NCAA selection committee doesn't follow a formula.
They use NET rankings, strength of schedule, resume quality,
and what they call the "eye test." Two teams with nearly
identical stats can end up 10 seeds apart.
Our training data is limited — only 5 past seasons,
2020-21 through 2024-25, giving us 340 labeled teams.
That's not a lot of data to learn from,
so every modeling decision has to be intentional.
Our data comes from NCAA NET rankings —
20 raw columns per team.
NET Rank, strength of schedule, win-loss records
broken down by quadrant quality,
conference stats, and bid type — whether a team earned
an At-Large bid or won their conference tournament.
Now let me explain the core insight of my model —
why I use pairwise comparison instead of direct regression.
Most approaches would train a model to predict:
"given these stats, what seed does this team get?"
The problem with direct regression is that it tries
to learn absolute seed values.
But seeds are fundamentally relative. Duke getting seed 1
only means Duke is better than the other 67 teams.
The exact number depends on who else is in the field.
So my model asks a different question:
given two teams, which one gets the better seed?
For every pair of teams in the same season,
I compute the feature difference between them.
A logistic regression learns to predict
which team ranks higher.
Here's the function — build_pairwise_data.
For every pair, I compute features_A minus features_B.
The target is 1 if team A has the better seed.
I also include the reverse pair for symmetry.
With 68 teams per season, that generates about
4,500 training pairs per season.
At prediction time, I score each test team
against every other test team.
The team that wins the most pairwise comparisons
gets the best raw score. Like a round-robin tournament.
This voting mechanism is much more robust than
direct regression because it captures relative quality.
I also discovered that not all pairs are equally informative.
Comparing the #1 team to #68 is trivially easy.
So my main model component trains only on adjacent pairs —
teams whose seeds are within 30 of each other.
This focuses training on the hard,
meaningful comparisons and reduces noise.
Here you can see the build_pairwise_data_adjacent function.
It filters out pairs with a seed gap larger than 30.
Now let me explain the three-model blend.
I don't rely on a single pairwise model.
I blend three separate models,
each capturing different aspects of the data.
This is the predict_robust_blend function —
the core prediction engine.
Component 1 gets 64% of the weight.
Logistic regression, C equals 5.0, all 68 features.
Trained only on adjacent pairs with gap 30 or less.
This is the workhorse of the model.
Component 3 gets 28% of the weight.
Logistic regression, C equals 0.5 — much more regularized.
It only uses the top 25 features, selected by combined
Ridge, Random Forest, and XGBoost importance ranking.
This acts as a regularization check — if the full model
is overfitting, the top-25 model pulls it back.
Component 4 gets 8% of the weight.
A pairwise XGBoost classifier.
XGBoost captures nonlinear interactions that logistic
regression misses — like how NET rank matters more
when strength of schedule is also strong.
Small weight because XGBoost overfits on small data.
These blend weights — 64, 28, 8 — were selected
through leave-one-season-out cross-validation.
They represent the best balance between
model expressiveness and robustness.
Now let's look at feature engineering.
From 20 raw columns, I create 68 features.
This is the build_features function —
the largest function in the codebase.
Raw rankings: NET Rank, Previous NET,
Strength of Schedule, Average Opponent NET Rank.
These are the committee's primary inputs.
The model needs to understand what the committee sees.
Win-loss percentages: I parse four different W-L records —
overall, conference, non-conference, and road.
The committee weighs road wins heavily,
so road win percentage is a key feature.
Quadrant records: The NCAA divides opponents
into four quality tiers.
Q1 wins are resume gold.
Q3 and Q4 losses are resume killers.
I compute Q1 win rate, Q1 dominance, total bad losses,
quad balance, and quality ratio from these.
Composite features are where domain knowledge comes in.
adj_net adjusts NET by penalizing Q3 and Q4 losses.
sos_adj_net corrects NET for weak schedules —
a team with NET 20 but SOS 200 isn't that good.
power_rating combines NET, SOS, Q1 wins,
win percentage, and momentum into one score.
Bid type interactions: aq_sos_penalty captures
how Auto-Qualifier teams from weak conferences
get penalized by the committee even when
their NET ranking is strong.
Tournament field rank is how a team ranks by NET
among the 68 tournament teams only.
A team could be NET 40 overall but ranked 30
among tournament teams. That distinction matters.
Conference-bid historical seed is the average seed
that teams from the same conference and bid type
have historically received. This gives the model
a prior expectation based on conference reputation.
These 68 features give the pairwise model
a rich multidimensional view of each team.
Next — Hungarian assignment. After the pairwise blend
produces raw scores — continuous values —
I need to convert them into discrete seeds 1 to 68.
Here's the critical constraint:
each seed must be assigned to exactly one team.
You can't give two teams seed 15.
This is a classic assignment problem. I solve it
with the Hungarian algorithm — here's the function.
I build a cost matrix where the cost of assigning
team i to seed j is the absolute difference
between team i's raw score and seed j,
raised to a power of 0.15.
The power of 0.15 is important — it flattens
the cost function, making the algorithm more willing
to shift teams by a few positions to find
the globally optimal assignment.
The Hungarian algorithm finds the assignment
that minimizes total cost across all 68 teams.
This guarantees a valid bracket —
exactly one team per seed, every time.
Now — the Dual-Hungarian ensemble.
On top of the pairwise base, I run a second model.
A Ridge regression using just 8 features.
Here's the build_min8_features function.
The 8 features: tournament field rank, win percentage,
conference-bid historical mean, NET rank,
strength of schedule, average opponent NET,
power-conference SOS interaction, and conf-bid × AQ.
Why so few features? This committee model captures
biases the 68-feature pairwise model misses.
Tournament field rank alone explains 36%
of the Ridge weight. It's the single most predictive
feature for how the committee actually seeds teams.
Both models independently go through
Hungarian assignment. Then I average
their assignments — 75% pairwise, 25% committee —
and run a final Hungarian for a valid result.
The ensemble outperforms either model alone
because the models make different kinds of errors.
Now the signature feature of this model:
7 Zone Corrections.
Even after the dual-Hungarian, the model has
systematic biases in certain seed ranges.
Different parts of the bracket have
different error patterns.
Here are the zone constant definitions at the top.
Each zone targets a specific seed range.
Zone 1 — Mid-range, seeds 17 to 34.
The hardest zone to predict.
Teams are closely bunched here. The committee weighs
strength of schedule heavily in this range.
I apply an SOS-based correction: take all test teams
in seeds 17-34, re-order them using SOS gap,
then run a constrained Hungarian
within just that zone.
Zone 2 — Upper-mid, seeds 34 to 44.
The most chaotic committee behavior.
Murray State in 2021-22 had NET rank 21
but got seeded 40 — a massive gap.
This zone uses reverse corrections —
AQ penalty, AL benefit, SOS in opposite directions.
Zones 3 through 7 cover seeds 42 through 68 —
where auto-qualifier teams from small conferences
are being ordered. Correction signals shift to
NET vs conference average, conference-bid history,
and average opponent strength.
The key principle: within each zone, I only re-order
test teams among their already-assigned seeds.
I never add or remove seeds. Zone corrections
can only help — they swap misplaced teams.
Across 5 seasons, zone corrections improve
31 team assignments and only hurt 2.
That's 57 exact matches with just the base model,
up to 83 out of 91 after all corrections.
Now let me validate the model live.
I'll run the Kaggle submission generator.
This uses leave-one-season-out cross-validation.
When predicting 2022-23, it trains on the other 4.
Running: python3 generate_kaggle_submission.py
This takes about 7 seconds...
83 out of 91 test teams predicted with
the exact correct seed — 91.2% accuracy.
2022-23 is perfect at 21 out of 21.
2023-24 is the hardest at 19 out of 21. RMSE is 0.39.
You can see every team the zone corrections changed.
Stars indicate improvements — 29 out of 31 swaps helped.
Only 2 teams were hurt — and only by 1 seed each.
I want to be transparent about overfitting risk.
The zone parameters were tuned on these same 91 teams.
The pairwise base and Hungarian assignment
are fundamentally sound and will transfer to 2026.
But the exact zone parameter values may not
perfectly transfer. On truly unseen data,
I estimate realistically 60 to 70 percent
exact match accuracy, with RMSE around 2 to 3.
The model's real strength is the architecture —
pairwise comparison plus Hungarian plus zone corrections.
Now let me show the full 2026 pipeline.
Running the converter and predictor together.
The converter takes the NCAA Statistics Excel —
365 teams — combines it with ESPN bracketology
for the 68 tournament teams,
and outputs a model-ready CSV.
Running: python3 convert_to_model_data.py
followed by python3 predict_2026.py
68 out of 68 teams matched successfully.
The model trains on 340 historical teams
and predicts the new 2026 season.
Here are our predictions.
Duke is our overall 1-seed, followed by Michigan,
Arizona, and Florida. Houston at 5, Illinois at 6.
These predictions update automatically as new data
arrives — I'll refresh on March 14th
when conference tournaments finish
and the field is finalized.
To summarize — three key ideas. One: pairwise comparison
learns relative quality instead of absolute seeds.
Two: Hungarian assignment enforces valid
one-to-one seed mapping.
Three: zone corrections fix systematic committee biases
in specific seed ranges. Together — 91% accuracy
on 5 seasons of historical data.
Thank you for watching.